Steve Fosdal

608-347-0014 steve@fosdal.net fosdal.net github.com/sfosdal linkedin.com/in/stevefosdal

Objective

As a software engineer with more than 20 years of experience, I am driven to architect and implement pragmatic solutions.

I seek an organization that wants the same and will provide novel and challenging opportunities so that I can bring my skills to bear, contributing to the organization's growth and mine.

Skills

Languages: Scala / Java / SQL / JSON / RegEx / Perl

Frameworks: Spark / Spark Streaming / Akka / Akka HTTP / Akka Cluster / Apache Camel / Scalatra /

ScalaTest / ScalaCheck / ScalaMock / gRPC

Storage: Kafka / RabbitMQ / Cassandra / ScyllaDB / MongoDB / MySQL / Postgres / Oracle

Tools: IntelliJ / DataGrip / CircleCI / Jenkins / Travis / Docker / Kubernetes / GitHub / GitLab /

sbt / ssh / DataDog / Splunk

AWS: EMR / Kinesis / Lambda / Athena / Redshift / CloudFormation / CloudWatch / EC2

Experience

Senior Technical Lead, Distributed Systems @ Tubi

Remote 2020 - Present

Scala / Akka / ScyllaDB / Postgres / Docker / Kubernetes / AWS-Kinesis / grpc

- Support and Enhance ML Pipeline
- Onboard new ML experiments
- Support and Enhance in-house A/B Switchback testing platform

Staff Engineer @ The Climate Corporation

Seattle, WA

2019 - 2020

Scala / Clojure / Java / Akka / Akka HTTP / Scalatra / MySQL / Postgres/ Docker / AWS

- Built out new microservice based platform
- Supported many legacy services in various JVM based languages
- Lead on the team in proposing/reviewing architecture and system changes

Co-founder @ Ghostwood Labs

Seattle, WA

2018 - Present

· Founded company specializing in codifying intuition using big data & machine learning

Senior Platform Engineer @ Apptentive

Seattle, WA

2018 - 2019

Scala / Spark / Akka / Akka Streams / Kafka / Cassandra / MongoDB / Docker / Kubernetes AWS: EMR / Kinesis / Athena / EC2

- Built out new platform based on Spark
- · Active participant in proposing and reviewing new architecture and system designs

Senior Data Engineer @ Avvo

Seattle, WA

2017 - 2018

Scala / Spark / Spark Streaming / Kafka / Cloudera / CircleCI / Docker AWS: Athena / CloudWatch / EC2 / EMR / Lambda

· Built backend service for real-time recommendations for related content

2020.09.16 v3.2.0

- · Created plan for migration from Cloudera Enterprise to native AWS services
- · Mentored engineers in Scala and Spark

Technical Reviewer @ Packt - Akka Cookbook

2017

Learn how to use the Akka framework to build effective applications in Scala https://www.packtpub.com/application-development/akka-cookbook

Solution Architect @ Slalom Consulting

Chicago, IL

2015 - 2017

Scala / Spark / Java / Spring / Eureka / Azure AWS: EMR / Kinesis / Lambda

- · One of two leads on a team of 14 for precision agriculture project
- · Responsible for data lake migration, design & development
- Mentored engineers in Scala

Technical Reviewer @ Packt - Mastering RabbitMQ

2015

Master the art of developing message-based applications with RabbitMQ https://www.packtpub.com/application-development/mastering-rabbitmq

Lead Engineer @ HERE Technologies

Chicago, IL

2010 - 2015

Scala / Java / Groovy / Perl / Akka / Akka Cluster / Spark / Apache Camel / Redis / Ehcache / RabbitMQ / Puppet AWS: EMR

- · Led team of engineers to build Akka based actor system for real-time traffic prediction
- · Worked with researchers to improve performance and quality of traffic algorithms, map matching, vehicle routing, and travel time allocation
- · Lead architect in the redesign of data collection framework

Lead Engineer @ University of Chicago

Chicago, IL

2009 - 2010

Java / PL-SQL / Perl / C# / jQuery

- · Recommended architecture for application and data warehouse development
- · Implemented PL-SQL enhancements to SunGard Advance

Senior Engineer @ Gundersen

La Crosse, WI

2008 - 2009

Java / PL-SQL / Perl / DICOM / Mirth / Tomcat / MySQL / GE-PACS / HL7

- Architected and developed application to perform batch migration of 10TB+ of historical medical imagery
- · Developed algorithm for patient matching and deduplication from multiple clinics

Lead Engineer @ UW-Madison

Madison, WI

1994 - 200

Cold Fusion / PHP / ASP / Visual Basic / JavaScript / JSP / Perl / PL-SQL / XSL / XPath / XQuery / Apache Tomcat / HL7 / OMNIS

- · Led team of 10 developers in creation of several interdependent J2EE based services
- · Implemented and supported integration of Oracle Financial Apps into existing services
- · Developed web-based scheduling and time recording tool, including recurring events, email notifications, work efficiency, and payroll reports

Education

Bachelor of Science in Physics @ UW-Madison

Madison, WI

1988 - 1993

- · Studied graduate level High Energy Physics, Computational Physics, and Mathematics
- Acknowledged for computational simulation work in: Charged Vortex Dynamics in Ginzburg-Landau Theory of the Fractional Quantum Hall Effect http://arxiv.org/abs/hep-th/9206073

2020.09.16